Are
[Music]
you
happy? Heat.
[Music]
Heat.
Heat. Heat.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the Ask Abijit Show.
Today is episode
237 live on YouTube. I hope everyone's
doing excellent, everyone's doing great.
Today I'm going to take questions that
you have asked in the comments and then
if there is time I will take questions
from the live chat as well if possible.
But before that let me see who all is
there on the live stream today. I can
see lots of people. Um I can see Dwanch
Singla. I can see Krishna Govinda Alfred
Gunat Bulay Udav Prattabora Surrender
Gupta Adity Kumar Singh Happy Soul
Kohish Tanju Krish Gupta Rangers Wolf
Geopolitical Dubai from Indor Pranov
Sony Grinder Gupta Zan HZ Gaming
Feminist Hunter Shivan Shanka
Pratamagarwal Tundra Rea Humbli Kiny R
Ash Ashish Pandel Vidi Manar Vikram Adi
Mr.
88ers 1813 Sahed Dir Akash Ba Dwanch
Singla Bloodmonger Creatin Happy Soul
Sergeant Skylin Abi Ram Ankur Sharaf
Pranav Sony Kapalin Raakai Samart
Tripati Shria Spitra Udav Pratag Bora
Vanos Spot feminist hunter Vinay Krishna
Suryan Kapel Kalyani Deshmuk Tan Chandra
Somi Jane Tjis B pranayal from Kolkata
Vik Adi, Zubon,
Eizang, Sunil, Chave, Shagun, Chopra,
hello Utsav, hello Diddy's
Dudu, Pratam Geopolitical, Dub again,
Sahil, Matio, Perez from Texas,
Sapratim, Duta, Aishek Chakraorti from
Bangladesh, Adi, Adihari, Sangram,
Nyak SN, Praar Gupta, Retun Na, Runyer,
Prashant, Bolian, uh, Joel, Joe, Udb,
Sharma, B but Odi Blitzray YT
Pratamarwal David Umong Bay uh you know
who from Kolkata Palab from Kolkata Mr.
Makavin, Anjali, Mari and so many other
people. So good evening to all of you.
Good day to all of you wherever you are.
And let's get going with the questions.
What questions do we have
today? And we have a question from
Geopolitical Dubai. Will scientists be
ever able to predict earthquakes? Will
there ever be such technology that can
allow scientists to predict earthquakes?
So there was an earthquake I think
yesterday I think right or day before
yesterday uh on the border of Myanmar
and Thailand. It was a 7.7 earthquake on
the RTOR scale and it caused a lot of
damage. So it would be great if you
could predict earthquakes, right? Then
we could alert people beforehand and it
would save a lot of lives and pro
possibly some property as well. But as
of today, we don't have the means to
predict earthquakes. Will it be possible
in the future? So to understand that,
let's understand what is the mechanism
that causes earthquakes. In a way, it's
like, you know, making meteorological
forecasts and predictions. when is it
going to rain in a certain part of the
world? What kind of weather conditions
will we have? And we have a lot of
weather data patterns that we that we
collect and we feed into supercomputers
and these computers then do the modeling
and they are able to give give us the
predictions of the next few days when it
comes to weather across the world, the
weather patterns. So to make these
predictions, these softwares, these
computers etc. these programs, they need
a tremendous amount of data, real-time
data, evolving data that allows them to
hone the model and to make predictions
into the future. And these predictions
typically work for the next few days,
but if you want to make a prediction
from for a week or two weeks down the
line, it may be something that's still
very difficult to do and it may not be
very accurate. So to make predictions of
weather in the atmosphere, we need
tremendous amounts of data of the
weather that exists currently. Now
earthquakes are caused by tectonic
activity by the movements of tectonic
plates under the surface of the earth. U
these tectonic plates are masses of of
the earth's crust that move very slowly
over time and they move they collide
they they grind past each other. that
move over each other. Some slide under
another. So sometimes you have one plate
sliding another another plate. And these
movements are what cause earthquakes.
These movements are caused by the flow
of
magma in the uh you know in the inter
internal part of the earth below the
mantle of the earth. Um yeah I'll not go
and show you the diagram of the of the
cross-section of earth of the earth but
that's how it works. So to be able to
make predictions of future earthquakes,
you need a tremendous amount of data of
uh the kind of uh activity that's
happening under the earth's surface. Uh
you'll need a lot of data about the flow
of the magma in below the mantle of the
mantle of the earth and you'll need data
off the mantle of the earth to that that
too. And that's all subsurface data.
Data about parts of the Earth that are
hundreds of kilometers below the
surface, tens of kilometers at least.
And we don't have sensors down there.
You would need tens of thousands of
sensors at various varying depths under
the Earth's surface to be able to make
reliable predictions of what's going to
happen in a certain part of the world.
Will there be an earthquake? Especially
in the parts of the world that are
called the that are tect that are
seismically active, tectonically active
areas where you have intersections of
various tectonic plates and one of the
these areas is called the ring of fire.
You know the area from the Andaman Sea
all the way to Indonesia through
Indonesia and all the way to Japan and
New Zealand and even the Andes region of
the of the Americas and the Rocky
Mountains regions and so on so forth. So
you will need a tremendous amount of
sensors, number of sensors, tens of
thousands of sensors under the earth's
surface at various points under the
earth's surface. All giving you feeding
you data in real time and more than that
you may need data about the movements
about the activity of the magma layer
that's way below the mantle of the earth
and that's essentially impossible to do
in today's scenario. And because we
don't have any of this data that's why
we cannot really make any accurate
predictions of earthquakes. In the
future it may be possible but at this
point in time it's next to impossible to
do that and that's why earthquakes are
still a huge problem but typically
earthquakes happen in tectonically
active regions parts of the earth. Uh
this earthquake that happened a couple
of days ago on the border between
Myanmar and Thailand that's unusual.
That's not an that's not a part of the
world that's typically prone to
earthquakes. So that was unusual. Uh but
yeah generally when you have when you
are living in a in an earthquakep prone
region you take precautions on a daily
basis. You build buildings you construct
buildings that are resilient and that
will be able to withstand earthquakes of
whatever magnitude maybe seven or eight
or whatever. In Japan I think you need
to be able to withstand earthquakes of
at least eight on the victor scale if
not higher and so on. So people who live
in such areas they take precautions but
it's always good to be able to predict
earthquakes which we currently are not
able to do. In the future it may be
possible but right now it's not quite
possible. Next question is by Infinite
406 U and Infinite 406 says choose one
uh history edition which is superior
Athens versus Spartans. I would say
Athens because Athens won in the end.
The Spartans did win the penopollesian
war but Athens did make a comeback let's
say in in 100 years time and over the
long term Athens was the one that lasted
more. So I would say Athens. Yeah. But
the Spartans obviously were superior in
their military uh tactics and strategies
and their military milit militaristic
lifestyle. But overall I would say
Athens was superior because it was a
more well-rounded culture, more
well-rounded city state, more culturally
relevant than Sparta. Sparta was
one-dimensional, all militaristic.
Athens had other stuff as well. I would
say overall Athens would be superior.
The Aimeid Aimeid Empire versus the Mad
Empire. The Mag Empire is the one that
preceded the Morian Empire. I would say
look the Mag Empire conquered most of
the subcontinent, right? Large part of
the subcontinent. the Aminids
they the thing about the Aminids and
various Indian empires whether it's the
Magada or the Moran Empire is that they
they were never
adversaries you see Indian empires like
the Morian Empire or the Mag Empire they
never tried to expand beyond the
subcontinent they only wanted to unify
uh the subcontinent under one political
rule which was theirs. When it comes to
the Aheimerid Empire, they were
expansionists, but they never ever
expanded eastwards towards India. They
always fought the the empires to the
west, whether it's the Greeks or
whoever, right? So, I would
say I would say it's a tie. Aminids
versus Magad or Moria. It's a tie. Uh
Chandra Gupta versus Caesar. Chandra
Gupta Moria is the founder of the Moria
Empire of the Moria dynasty. He had the
help of his great mentor Shri Vishnu
Gupta Chanaka and he established the
beginnings of an empire that would
eventually be the greatest empire we
ever saw in the subcontinent. more or
less not probably the greatest maybe the
Kushan was greater empire was greater
but okay uh it was one of the greatest
of all empires in the subcontinent and
it gave rise to this great cultural
efflloresence and so on so forth right
so uh so the founder was chundraupta
moria when it comes to Caesar he was a
military conqueror and he conquered vast
territory probably larger than the
subcontinent so from a purely uh
expansionist perspective from a from a
territorial conquest perspective Caesar
was greater He was one of the greatest
generals of all time. But from a
civilizational perspective, I would say
Chandra Gupta was greater. So it depends
on which way you look at it. Caesar was
a conqueror. Uh he was interested in
conquest in in wealth. Why did he
conquer? Because it gave him vast
amounts of of of territory from which to
extract resources like Hispania from
which he got a tremendous amount of gold
and so on. And that increases prestige
in Rome. his overall objective was to be
number one the number one man in Rome
and that's why he he conquered so much
and because he had all these legions at
his disposal and legions to maintain
legions you need a tremendous amount of
resources money that's also another
reason for watch for behind his
conquests but his conquests were
incredibly destructive they resulted in
what you would today call genocide
uh so yeah but from a conquest
perspective Caesar was greater from a
allround perspective Ive I would say
perhaps Chandra Gupta Moria was was
greater perhaps. Uh so it depends on
which way you look at it. Uh next
Samudra Gupta versus Napoleon. Samudra
Gupta knew when to stop. His entire life
his entire career as emperor was one
extended military conqu campaign and he
conquered the whole of the subcontinent.
He subdued all the all the kingdoms to
the south, north, everywhere. He
launched uh a dual conquest of the south
part of India which was u a landbased
conquest with a parallel naval conquest.
So he was one of the all-time great
Samud Gupta.
Napoleon so samud Gupta wanted to unify
the subcontinent and he did not engage
in want and destruction and all that.
Napoleon just wanted to rule the world.
He did not know where to stop and that
is what eventually led to his downfall.
Uh I would say Samudra Gupta was
greater. He was a much greater ruler and
he was I would say as good or if not
better than Napoleon in uh his military
strategies and tactics and the way he
conducted his conquest. So I would say
Samoda wins
that. Breaking Bad versus True Detective
season 1. I would say I've seen both
actually. I've seen Breaking Bad. I've
seen True Detective season 1. Uh, Trudy
Detective season 1 is probably one of
the greatest pieces of uh of of uh uh
cinema. Is it cinema? It's it's a TV
series. Uh it was great. It's it's
pretty dark. It's about serial killers
and stuff. But it's really wellm made.
But overall, I would say Breaking Bad is
is is superior because it lasted I don't
know how many five, six seasons,
whatever it was. I think overall
sustained excellence. You saw that in
Breaking Bad. when it comes to to
detective the subsequent seasons I hear
aren't that good there u n versus
egalitarian philosophy look I am no
great fan of niche or whatever but uh if
you were to talk about freed nichch's
philosophy uh what do I what comes to
mind god is dead he famously proclaimed
that god is dead he he said that the
rise of science and secularism in the
west in the in the world was causing the
decline of religious belief and this has
created a crisis of of uh crisis of
values, crisis of meaning, crisis of
what's the purpose of life, all of that.
So he said God is dead. He uh said that
we are now living in a world that has no
inherent meaning. It has no inherent
purpose. He called it nihilism and he
believed that it could perhaps be a
starting point for creating new values
and meaning. But I'm not sure where we
have gone with that. And he spoke about
something called the will to power. He
said that there is a fundamental drive
in all living beings in all living
things. We called it the willed power
which is your personal quest your
personal uh striving for growth for
overcoming your own limitations and all
that. So he called that the will to
power and he also came up with this
concept of the uber mench the superman
which is this concept of a higher or
more powerful type of human being who's
able to create their own values and live
in live according to their own values
and according to their
uh their own will okay and impose their
will on the world and create and give
the world purpose and and meaning and
all of that. So these are the things
that uh Nietze spoke about. There's a
lot more to Nietze than just this. So
that's Nietze. He said that you know the
world is not is not um that he said that
all humans aren't equal. He did not
believe in equality. He said that some
are superior, some are not and it
depends on how you live your life and if
you have the will will to power how much
of the will to power you have. Everyone
doesn't have the same will to power.
Some people have low agency. They will
just be passive spectators in life. They
will be supporting characters. And some
people have more agency. They'll get
things done no matter what. They'll find
a way. And these are the the uh these
are the
heroes the in life the central
characters in in in in life right uh so
all people aren't equal. Nature did not
believe in equality. And egalitarian
philosophy says that everyone is equal
and all and so on so forth. Listen where
what do I believe? I believe that
everybody should have the same rights.
Everybody should have the same rights
and should be treated the same as per as
per uh whatever principles we live by
whether it is law, a constitution or
whatever. Everybody should have the same
starting point and the same treatment.
But I don't believe all humans are
equal. Some I mean look look at human
beings around you. Some are tall, some
are short, some are more intelligent,
some are less intelligent, some are
richer, some are poorer, some are just
capable of doing more, some are not so
capable. So, egalitarian philosophy uh
you know the foundations are good.
Everybody should be given the same
rights. No matter what is their lineage,
what is their uh you know status at
birth, whatever parentage they come
from, whatever their so-called class in
society, everybody should get the same
rights and all. I completely believe in
that. But I also don't believe that all
humans are equal. Some people are just
different. Everybody's different, right?
I mean, why do we uh why do we have the
Olympics? Why do we have the World Cup?
It's not to celebrate equality. is to
celebrate inequality. It's to is to
celebrate those who are the best. They
are the ones who win. Uh the second, you
know, the runners up medal is is not the
medal you want. You want the winner's
medal. So yeah, so I would say I I would
probably go a little bit more with
nature than with egalitarian philosophy.
But I do I do agree with the fact that
everybody should have the same rights
and um same treatment, right? And good
treatment and good rights. Yeah. Uh,
Darwinian society versus a Dharmic
society. Obviously a Dharmic society.
Darwinian principles do apply to the
world obviously you know the survival of
the fittest the ones who strive more do
better. So and so on but Dharmic
philosophy means everybody should be
treated with compassion and so on. So
it's kind of a continuation of the
previous one. I would obviously always
go for a dharmic society.
Right.
Okay. Okay. This is a big question.
Immran says, "Can you explain sir why
these kinds of things happen? What
things?" Let's see. If you read the
shahame ofi, the author mentioned an
area called uh Ariana. Yes. And it
cities and palaces. He mentioned uh
Ariana's palaces like Kabulistan,
Tkaristan, Zabulistan, Ghazni, Bameyan.
All of these exist in present day
Afghanistan, not Iran. And he has
written the names of two large kingdoms
which are Ariana and Paris which is
Persia like two different countries.
Yeah. He kind of may have done that.
Yeah. And he also said that people of
Ariana speak the Dhari language and the
people of Par speak uh Persian language
pari language. In most of the poems is
written like Mardasa's story stanza nine
whatever that is. I don't know how to
read that. I used to be able to but no
longer. So in English it says it's
inappropriate for us to say bar 10,000
in pari parsi language. It's better for
us to say dah hazar 10,000 in the dari
language. According to this verses, Dari
language was not the language of Parus
and the Parsei language is extinct by
empires of Ariana. Yet both are the same
language family but different languages.
Because of this, the king of Persia,
Raza Sha Pali changed his country's name
Persia to Iran and the language name
Dari to Persians for making the history
richer and richer. In the Shaame, the
details are very clear. Okay, very
interesting story you bring in. What's
the deal with the Shaame? Right. The
Shaame was written by Ferdosi.
uh it was com it was written between 9
about 980 AD to about 1010 AD over a
period of about 30 years. It was written
by Firsi. Now when Ferdosi started
writing this this book the Shahame the
record of the kings of Persia the record
of the entire history of Persia. when he
started writing this uh the uh
geopolitical entity in power in Persia
in the region was the Samantha Empire
which was a Persian
Empire. But around the late 990s maybe
around 999 AD 80 or some somewhere
around that time the Samid Empire was
overthrown by a Turk Empire. the
Gaznavid the Gaznavid empire you know
Mahmud of Gazni that that guy the Turk
who has a pretty dark history in India
we know that so uh so Mahmud of so the
Gaznavi empire takes over from the
Samarit empire and Mahmud of Gazni kind
of becomes the patron of
uh Ferdosi h and then ferdosi continues
writing the shaam and he concludes
around 1010 AD now when you have a
patron who is this conqueror, a
foreigner, a Turk, not a Persian. You
will find that Mahmud of Gazni would
have been less interested in tales from
Persian
history. He would not have been
interested in that. He would have been
interested in self- glorification and he
would have expected that the writer of
the Shaame Ferdosi would glorify him and
the region he came from. And the region
he was he came from was was presently
Afghanistan. He occupied Afghanistan. He
was a he was a foreigner. Even in
Afghanistan, he was a Turk. He was not
Afghan. He was not pun. He was a Turk.
So uh so you have to understand
that the Shahame cannot be treated as a
completely factual book. There was
politics at the time that would have
encouraged let's say Ferdosi to kind of
write things in a certain manner. But
it's also true like you say that a lot
of these places that he talks about are
present day Afghanistan not present day
Persia and that's that's just the way it
is. So uh my point is you cannot take uh
the shaame as a completely historical
absolutely uh unquestionable historical
text. Uh and a lot of the stuff is kind
of look I'll tell you what Ferdosi was
not a big fan of the Arabs. He was not a
even a big fan of the Turks but he had
to operate under those those
circumstances. He was not even a Muslim
by the way. Fossi he did not write very
nice things about the Arabs who
conquered Persia. He wrote pretty sad
things you know about the condition that
Persia was was in under Arabic rule and
then all of that. Um so you have to
understand this there's layers of things
over over here and if you look at the
Shaame of
Ferdosi he essentially if you if you
look at the origins of Persia mentioned
in the Shaame they're very interesting.
Let's let's uh bring an English version
of the Shaame on the screen and just
take a look at what what's written a
little bit of that.
Uh where is the Shaame? Shaame the
Shahame the the epic of kings. Uh let's
make it like this. Okay. So it it starts
with it starts with the origin of of
Persia essentially and uh it talks about
the first king Caillum and uh what
happens after that? Then you have hushen
and
aftersh you have jamshed. So jamshed is
yamak yama. It is yama of the rigveda.
Then if we go further beyond that there
is zah and zah is is is depicted as a
dragon a snake and the person who
destroys eventually. Zahak is a person
who is referred to as
uh Feredun in this text. Feredun right
feridun the person who Ferdosi refers to
as faridon was originally called thun in
Persian and thrun is also
calledyaun and it is the same person as
a so-called minor divinity in the rigida
which is traa and if you read the rigida
it's kind of interesting
because at times portrayed fighting the
great serpent vitra and of course it
Indra who destroys vitra but over here
it is traa in the shaame who destroys
this serpent zahak who is an Arabic
version of vitra and so on. So if you
look at the original uh if you look at
the initial portion of the shaame it
kind of mirrors the original texts of
India which tells you that there was a
very deep ancient
uh uh common origin of the Persians and
the Indians right uh so it's like that
my my point overall is to to what you
mentioned you have to be careful in
interpreting the shaame it is
uh it's a complicated text and It the
way it was written depend it was it was
influenced by the politics of the time
and Ferdosi had to kind of uh take
special care to make his overlord Mahmud
of Ghazni happy to keep him happy and
for that he had to it is alleged that
Mahmud Gazni promised to give Sha to
give Fredosi one gold coin for each
verse or something that he wrote in in
the Shaame and to get that obviously he
has to write things that are that that
makes that make this
happy, right? Uh so it could have
influenced the way the shaame was
written. So it is not it is I mean it is
the oldest text in the Persian language
that we have today whether you call it
Dari or whatever. Yeah, Dari. There are
definitely two versions of of Persian
very similar languages. One is the
Persian that is spoken in Afghanistan
which is called Dari and then you have
the Persian language. There may be some
some dissimilarities but overall they're
part of the same language family like
you say but so the the shaame is the
only ancient text from Persia
essentially that survives. Persia would
have had lots of ancient texts zoroastan
text etc which would have been destroyed
by the Arabs when they conquered Persia.
So Persia's downfall essentially started
with the conquest of Alexander uh which
destroyed the Akimeish empire and they
took the the Greeks took out all of the
wealth from Parapur Persales they melted
all the gold all the silver they would
have destroyed they they burned P
parapur which would have burned all the
books and all so a lot of the ancient
history of Persia is destroyed because
of all of this and that's why kind of
the oldest text that is available for
reference is the shaame but you have to
be careful with reading it. You cannot
interpret it literally. That's the
point. Okay. Uh questions about the
immigration the foreigner in immigration
bill Boruto and the Brahar Gupta. What's
your take on the new foreigner and
immigration bill and what are your views
on the latest immigration foreigners
bill 2025 introduced by the government
of India in the parliament? Do you think
it will be effective in preventing
illegal immigration in India? So let's
take a look at this bill. I have uh uh
found the bill. Let's put that on the
screen and let's briefly take a look at
what this bill says. Uh let's take this
out and we can see the whole thing. So
this is the bill and it has various
chapters and various sections and
clauses and so on. This is what the bill
is. So now what does this bill say is
the question. So if you look at clause
20, where is clause 20? Let's go all the
way down to clause 20. Where is clause
20? This is clause 20. So this
essentially broadly defines what
constitutes contravention of this act
including being in India without valid
documentation. Uh that's there is that's
clause 20. Clause 21 it essentially
provides for penalties for being in
India without valid travel documents up
to 5 years imprisonment and five lakh
rupees fine. Then you have clause 23
clause 23A which addresses foreigners
who remain in any ind area in India for
a period extending the period for which
the visa was issued and who stay in
India without a valid passport or
without travel
documents. Then um there is a clause 29.
Let's look at clause 29. It essentially
empowers the central government to
direct the removal of a foreigner from
India for controvention of any of the
provisions of this act. So we can deport
people who uh contravene the provisions
of this act. So this essentially
provides a mechanism to the government
of India for the deportation of illegal
immigrants. Now if you go back upstairs
uh to where is the clause 16? Is it
clause 16? So clause 16 essentially puts
the burden of proof uh of proving that
you uh that a person is not a foreigner
uh on the individual concerned. So uh
this makes it more challenging for
undocumented illegal immigrants to
contest any actions taken by the
government. In court you go to the court
and say that the government is doing
this. It is very oppressive. Then the
burden of proof is on the person to
prove that this person is is not a
foreigner. Right? Then what else do we
have? So essentially uh foreigners
according to this act foreigners who are
ordered to leave can be required to be
kept in specific places set aside for
illegal foreigners. Uh this bill
provides for the regulation of these
facilities like maintenance and
discipline and all that. Then u so these
uh provisions they create a framework
for holding foreigners in a certain
place pending their uh removal. Uh let's
look at some more clauses of this act.
Clause 33. Where is clause 33? It's
here. So, clause 33 gives the central
government powers to exempt any person
or class of people from the provisions
of the act. Uh so, you could create
theoretically theoretically you could
create some provisions or some some
exemptions for certain categories of
illegal immigrants if you want. Uh let's
say you have Tibetans who have come into
India uh in the past, you know, without
valid travel documents fleeing from
Chinese and Tibet. So maybe you could
create an exemption for those people if
the government so desires, right? Uh and
so on. So essentially this act
uh this so it's it's a good act I would
say. Yeah. The emphasis uh is on
providing the government with various uh
broad powers. It will provide the
government various broad powers to to
remove uh illegal immigrants and it
places significant responsibilities on
carriers who transported the these
individuals into India. But I don't as
far as I have seen it doesn't seem to
have any special provisions for
addressing the very complicated issue of
long-term
illegal infiltrators who are residing in
India. People who have been residing in
India for 40 50 years and their
descendants are also living in India. I
don't see uh thus far I have not seen
anything that uh any kind of provision
for addressing that situation. So when
when you have uh Bangladeshes who have
been illegal who have illegally come to
India and who have been living in India
for 30 40 50 whatever years there are
descendants that children grandchildren
are also living in India. How to deal
with that situation because we'll have
millions of those maybe 100 million of
those. What do we do with that with
those people? How do we address that
situ situation? I'm not sure I've seen a
solution or any provision for that. The
same goes for with the tens with the
hundreds of thousands of cookies who
have come into into India in the past
few decades. What to do with them? So I
it's a good start I would say but uh
maybe a little more maybe required when
u it comes to addressing those uh large
challenges that we face. I mean the
biggest problem we have in India is that
maybe 100 million illegal infiltrators
who are residing in various parts of
India who have been settled all across
the country and who have fake
documentation which may actually not be
fake. They may have illegally obtained
real documentation other cards and
whatnot. How do we deal with that? So I
think it's a good start and uh kudos to
the government for doing that and let's
see how they deal with the bigger
problems hopefully using this bill or
maybe uh some some other measure. We'll
see about that. So that's what I can say
about this bill right now.
Yeah. Mr. 88 says is it fair to say that
the what the cookies are trying to
achieve in Manipur is to create their
own version of Israel which will later
be used by the US. Okay, look this issue
of the illegal uh infiltrators in
Manipur, the cookies, it's a
geopolitical issue. It is not a local
law and order problem. It's a
geopolitical issue which is part of a
much bigger game that's being played. So
the project is called project K cookie
land for Christ whatever you want to
call it. Uh the objective ideally for
for whoever is doing this is to create
an artificial new nation cookie land out
of parts of India, Myanmar sorry India
which is Misoram and Manipur mostly
Manipur uh and also parts of Burma and
also parts of Bangladesh. That was the
original plan. Now Bangladesh is already
on board. It's a vasal city of the US.
Um so uh there is that and
u the mechanism is very simple. The
borders are open between India and
Myanmar. So bring in just push in
hundreds of thousands of illegal
immigrants who will reside in Manipur
over overrun the state and you set up
thousands of new villages almost
overnight. So you've created facts on
the ground, you occupy the territory and
then you claim that these people are
oppressed
minorities and the moment you start
talking about minorities of a foreign
religion of an Abrahamic religion then
you know the government of India will
take two steps back because the western
media and the western governments have
created this huge human cry and noise
over the past few years of oppressed
minorities in India. So the moment you
claim that these people who have come in
illegally are oppressed
minorities then the government of India
has to you know gets
defensive. So they've already created
facts on the ground. They occupy
tremendous amounts of territory. They
claim to be oppressed foreigners. They
claim to have been living here for from
time
immemorial. Right? So how do we deal
with the situation? That's the problem.
Right? So I don't know about a new
version of Israel or any such thing but
it's definitely uh being puppet mastered
from the west. Uh the church is very
much involved in this. This is very
that's very open. It's not a big secret
and various uh American organizations,
NOS's, state sponsored things, you know,
quasi
governmental organizations etc are all
involved in this. Uh and lot of people
are on on their payroll. Uh you will
even see Indians certain Indians who are
supporting this this project project K.
you will find uh retired paramilitary
forces personnel some some of them who
are also supporting this lots of
prominent media people are supporting
the this this illegal inf infiltration
and all so yeah it's it's a huge uh
challenge for India it's a huge pressure
point for on India from the west from
the US uh and uh yeah the situation will
have to be dealt with and and what
happens is that it is the uh it is the
it is the uh natives, native
inhabitants who suffer. They are the
ones who suffer and that's the situation
right now. So it it's going to take a
while to solve this problem. Um the
temptation will always be from the
government's perspective to just impose
order but not law and justice. Justice
means you evict the illegal immigrants
from India. Uh but that is going to be
challenging. So right now they just want
to have law and order more order than
law because illegal immigrants live
squatting on Indian territory is not law
but yeah so it's going to be a big
challenge for
India. Okay lots of questions about
Diego Garcia uh lost child Nachikit Jay
Raman Zuboniz and
Vikramat. Why are B2 stealth bombers in
Diego Garcia? Is the US going to attack
Iran? Seven B2 stealth bombers were
deployed at Diego Garcia earlier this
week. Uh the US just deployed the B2
stealth bomber in the Garcia. Is there
anything brewing in the Indian Ocean?
Trump has deployed stealth fighters in
the Garcia to tackle Houthis. Is the
Gulf headed for a new phase of war after
October 7, 2023? Iran just unveiled its
hidden missile city. Okay, for those who
are not aware, let's go to the map.
Where is the map? We have to unveil
unleash the map. Let's put the map on
the screen and discover where Gigartha
is. I've spoken about it many times but
let's take a look at it again. So we
know where India is. We know where the
Indian Ocean is. Let's go south of the
equator. So we have the Lakship Islands
here uh of the west coast or southwest
coast of India. South of the Lakshmi
Islands you have the Maldives
archipelago which is a continuation of
the same uh
archipelago and south of the Maldives
you have the Chaos Archipelago which is
also part of the same geographical
region and it's now called the British
Indian Ocean Territory it's illegally
occupied by Britain and they they are
doing this fake transfer of power to
Mauritius which is not going to change
anything on the ground so this is Diego
Garcia which if you look at it it has a
naval base and an air force base. It is
uh used by the US even though it
technically uh is occupied by the UK.
Now if you look at the naval base over
here wherever it is u it is capable of
accommodating aircraft carriers. That's
how big the naval base is and the air
force base is obviously very visible. If
you if you take take a look at the
dimensions
uh it is 3 and a half 3.6 6 km long
which can accommodate the heaviest and
largest of strategic bombers and
whatnot. So it's a very powerful tool of
of power projection for the US in
India's own backyard and they use it to
project power across the Indian Ocean
region across ranging from the straight
of Malaka all the way to the Persian
Gulf and the Gulf of Aden. That's the
deal. That's the gotha. Okay. So now uh
apparently the US is deploying uh
certain classes of aircraft to Diego
Garcia which is B2 stealth
bombers and recently we've heard that
Trump has unleashed uh military uh Trump
has unleashed air strikes on the Houthis
in Yemen uh because the Houthis are kind
of u uh interdicting access. Once again
let's go to the map. The Houthis are
kind of interdicting access to uh the
Red Sea region because they dominate the
Bab al-Mandip strait which is this
little geopolitical choke point over
here. Very important choke point which
connects the Red Sea to the Gulf of Adan
and the and the Indian Ocean. And for
those of you who will say it's not the
Indian Ocean, it's the Arabian Sea.
Please learn some geography. Okay. So uh
the Yemenes, the Houthis, the Ansarah
faction, they are the ones who are
interdicting access uh to the US and
other western powers to this region and
that's why Trump has unleashed uh air
strikes on their military uh uh
strategic uh capabilities. So that's
what's happening and it's most likely
that this uh these air strikes were
conducted from aircraft carriers in the
region.
Uh but yes, having uh B2 stealth bombers
in the in in the at Garcia gives
the US additional capabilities to to
strike at the Houthis or whoever else
they would like to strike at. Okay. So
I'm not going to speculate as to who
it's for, uh what they're planning. I
don't think it's that easy to to attack
Iran, which is Iran is not a pushover.
they have tremendous uh capabilities
when it comes to missiles and drones and
they'll be able to look there are so
many US military bases in the region
which could uh you know become targets
of Iranian response if if Iran is is
targeted by American air strikes. Uh
yes, Iran has recently uh unveiled a
hidden missile city underground missile
city or some kind of uh installation of
the some kind. Uh so I'm not sure what
the plan is. Maybe it's all about the
Houthis. Maybe it's a message to other
powers in the region. There are certain
other powers in the region as well,
right? Uh maybe it's a message to those
powers. Let's see. Uh I'm not going to
speculate as to what this could be. One
potential target obviously is Iran. The
other potential target is the Houthis in
Yemen. I don't think of I cannot think
of any other active adversaries the US
has in the region. It's Iran. It's the
Houthis. Syria is done and dusted.
They've done regime change operation.
They have a new Zalinski in place whose
name is what? Al Jolani or something, a
local
Zalinski. So Syria is taken care of. Uh
you don't need B2 cell members to deal
with Hamas obviously. So it's either
Iran or the Houthis or maybe it's a
message to somebody else, somebody
bigger in the region. Well, I don't
know. Can't
say.
Right. Prane Paul says with Trump's
presidency having already influenced
global geopolitics significantly what
larger shifts in the balance of power
can we see unfolding this decade in the
2020s we already halfway through how
might the ripple effects of his policies
continue to shape global alliances trade
and security beyond his
tenure right so Trump is going to be in
power until what uh he came to power
this year 2025 so until
2029 right he's going to be in power
until 2029 four years 3 and a half years
to go roughly give or take. I think it's
still early days so let's say four years
to go and he's already doing a lot he's
already upended a lot of things and uh
he's talking about Greenland is he's
already taken over Panama the Panama
Canel black has taken over so it's kind
of take over by the US the Panama Canal
u he's talking about Canada he's talking
about Europe all kinds of things going
on so what shifts in the balance of
power can we see in the next four years
uh I'll tell you the next four years is
going to see a complete rearrangement of
the geopolitical chess board globally.
Uh we are once again into the age of
empires. You know, nation
states, nation states, the so-called
rules-based global world order, all of
that is going to become very soon a
thing of the past. The US is now
behaving like an empire. It's not
behaving like a responsible nation
states state. It's talking about
gobbling up Greenland. is talking about
making Canada the 51 first state and
much more. So the US is going to change
the world order greatly. Trump is going
to show the world, teach the world what
geopolitics really is, what great power
geopolitics is all about, what hard
power is. So one thing we're going to
see is that Europe is going to become a
backwater. Okay, Europe is going to
become a global backwater. They have
some economic heft and all but they are
declining. Uh the Ukraine war has
significantly changed things in the in
in Europe. Uh Europe's economy is not no
longer doing well. Um uh to to have a
booming economy, you need a lot an
inexhaustible supply of cheap energy
which no longer is there because of the
Nordstream issue.
Um and uh Europe is going to have to is
going to be made to pay more for its
defense. Right now see the past 60 70
years Europe did not spend anything on
defense. Everything was taken care of by
the US. So the all the European nations,
the EU nations, they essentially became
welfare states and police states. Okay,
you may not realize that if you go to
Europe, it's a police state. So these
are welfare states where people don't
have to work very hard. They don't have
to innovate. They don't have to do
anything. The US will take care of
everything. big daddy. But now that is
not going to be no no longer the case.
So Europe is going to become a global
backwater slowly gradually but you're
going to it's going to be more and more
visible and they are kind of push trying
to push back against that but they don't
have any any real teeth in doing that.
It's all bark no bite unfortunately
sadly for the Europeans. So Europe is
declining. Um Russia is becoming more
and more relevant.
Um, China obviously is definitely
relevant and India is the fourth uh
sovereign nation. So there are four
sovereign entities right now in the
world. The US, Russia, China and India
and India sovereignty is is kind of
being threatened right now in a variety
of ways. The Manipur issue is is a good
example of that and other things. So uh
so you're going to see a complete uh you
know it's not going to be a bipolar
tripolar world. be
a it's not going to be a multipolar
world for sure. The only way you will
have a multipolar world if you is if you
have 20 nations with nuclear weapons
then you have a multipolar world but
that's not the case right so you're
going to see the co coallescence of the
world into multiple blocks you have
Russia China strange bed fellows but
they are together India is going to be
somewhere in between the east and the
west India's India's population is very
westernized
uh and uh maybe India will be made to uh
make a choice It's either us or them.
That sort of thing. Trump may do that.
Uh we'll see about that.
Uh so yeah, that's the kind of thing you
will see. So you're going to see the
decline of Europe. The the US is become
is going to become a more imperial kind
of power. Uh and you're going to see a
lot of great power politics. You know,
naked displays of hard power. Hopefully
no wars. And you may see a an escalation
of the cold war between the US and
China. The US has tried to deny China
all kinds of technology especially in in
in the realm of semiconductors, silicon,
all of that. But the Chinese have
overcome that and they now have their
own lithography machines which which
means that they can make chips that are
among the best in the world right now.
India is trying to start the game now
becoming to become
a semiconductor power but it's about we
are about a decade you
know we yeah it will take a decade for
us to reach that stage
uh so it's going to be challenging for
India so
um we're going to see that sort of world
in the in the future the US is going to
become a space power maybe a hyper power
AI may be the transformative technology
that changes everything and Uh yeah, if
if AI is the is the deciding factor,
then it's going to be the US versus
China. Nobody else is in the fray. India
is not in the fray. Russia is not not in
the fray. The Europeans are trying
something, but let's Yeah, they're not
in the same league as the Americans and
the Chinese.
So if AI is the deciding factor, it's
going to be a straight race between the
US and China. If space is the deciding
factor, the US is leagues ahead of
everybody else. So it's advantage US.
the Chinese may be able to catch up
technologically from an AI perspective
at least. Um, and let's see what India
does. We are way behind, but yeah, let's
see. And Russia doesn't seem to be in
the fray, but maybe they have something
up their sleeve. So, that's the kind of
world we're going to see. Lots of these
uh
old great powers are going to fall down
fall down the wayside and it's going to
be essentially four nations, four major
nations. And out of those four major
nations, India is the smallest power as
of
now. Balram Putin says, "If history has
shown that the strongest empires often
collapse due to internal power struggles
rather than external threats, then if
the US is considered an empire, why does
there appear to be no significant power
struggle with within its deep state? And
if such a struggle were to arise, what
would be the potential causes?"
Look, typically empires last 250, 300
years or so. Kingdoms, empires,
whatever. Some empires last longer. The
Roman Empire lasted much longer and so
on. So maybe the US, see, I'll tell you
when it comes to hard power, the US is
right now at the pinnacle of hard power.
The US has never been as powerful as it
as it has been until today. So maybe the
US empire is just reaching its peak. And
when you're reaching it, your peak,
there's no power struggle. Everything is
h everything is good. You have an
external enemy right now China. So all
all all all all the focus is going to be
on China and Russia and to some extent
on India to ensure that India doesn't
become a future great power 20 30 years
down the future. So so make sure take
care of India right now. So all the
threats when it comes to the US are
external and when you have big external
threats everything is is going to be in
order inside internally. Yes, you have a
decline of of cultural values and living
standards in the US, but that can be
taken care of because the US is also a
police state. So, they can deal with
their citizens.
Um, yeah. So, maybe it's because the US
is destined to last another 200 300
years as as as an empire in which case
you will not see any power struggle.
Everything doesn't have to happen right
now, right? Maybe it'll happen 100 years
down the line, maybe 150 years down the
line. Because we are living in this
moment doesn't mean that everything has
to happen right now. Right? Maybe there
is some power struggle. There's always
some politics going on in any empire.
The deep state is an invisible entity.
We don't quite know who makes up the
deep state. Who are the individuals and
so on. We don't quite know. And it is in
their interest not to give up their
power. So maybe they have things very
much under control. They are firmly in
control of the reigns. In which
case it makes sense to see what we are
seeing right now that the US doesn't
have any such issues. uh if in the
future such a struggle were to arise,
what could it be the potential causes?
If in the see typically when empires are
in are are unchallenged for a very long
time and they have no more enemies left,
that's when the decay sets in. As long
as there's a wolf out the out of out of
outside the door or a pack of wolves,
there's no decay that sets in. Right?
So in the future if the US becomes the
sole power and all other powers fall
down the wayside and everybody becomes
irrelevant the US becomes a
hyperpower then you could see
potentially something happening down the
line let's say the US becomes you know
develops artificial super intelligence
which makes it technologically
uncatchable and they develop godlike
technologies magicike technologies that
nobody can catch up with then all other
powers will become irrelevant and then
let's say the US goes and conquer Mars
and sets up uh uh you know multiple
bases on Mars, millions of people there.
Then in the future, Mars may in the
future declare independence and then you
may have a situation like uh the US
declaring independence from Great
Britain in the 18th century and then you
may have a conflict of that kind
perhaps. So that's something you could
see in the future or maybe something
else. We can only speculate at this
point. But at this point the US is at
the pinnacle of its power of its hard
power. It's never been as powerful as it
it is today and it has significant
adversaries outside. One is Russia, one
is China and in that situation you will
probably not see a decline
u or a collapse of the US. Of course,
one can be one, you know, anything's
possible. Uh but it's unlikely. It's
less likely from my perspective. Maybe
I'm wrong. Maybe you'll see something
else happening. We'll see. We'll see
about that.
Okay, Ankita Kachop says Brussels
advises US Brussels has advised EU
citizens to be prepared with 3 to 7 days
emergency supplies in order to face any
potential crisis. Are they planning to
go to war with
Russia? Yes. So one hears that Brussels
is making such statements and advising
its citizens to have to stock up on on
essentials, essential commodities and
have enough supplies to last let's say a
week or so in case of any
unforeseen scenarios or situations which
obviously is an illusion to a potential
warlike situation. And who could the the
EU go to war with in the continent?
Obviously not the US. They're talking
about Russia. So then the question
arises, is the EU planning to go to war
with Russia? My question is this, is the
EU capable of going to war with Russia?
Do they have the armed forces? Do they
have the the weapons systems? Do they
have sufficient ammunition? Do they have
the money? The truth is they have none
of these things. They may have some
money, but they are completely reliant
on the US for their defense, right? and
they don't have the the funds or the
supplies or the stockpiles of ammunition
needed to to to to carry on a sustained
military campaign against
Russia. The Russians have been fighting
this war for the past 3 years. They've
built up the war economy. So to be able
to fight a long
war or even a short war, you need a war
economy. You need your entire industrial
infrastructure to be fully invested in
the war effort. factories to produce
tanks, factories to produce missiles,
factories to produce bullets, factories
to produce machine guns, factories to
produce shells, howitzer shells, uh
everything that that you need in terms
of equipment from a military
perspective, your entire industrial
infrastructure should be able to handle
all of that. That's called a war
economy. That's what you had in the
Third Reich in the 1930s and 40s. That's
what they developed. That's what they
built up and that's what Russia has been
forced to do the past 3 years. So Russia
is now a welloiled fighting machine. Is
the EU capable of uh fighting the
Russians and if they start a war with
the Russians and the Russians say
enough, okay, I'm going to now roll my
tanks into Europe, are the Europeans in
a position to to stop them to stave off
such such a push from Russia. The the
that's the question the Europeans have
to ask themselves. Without US
intervention, can they survive? The US
is in no mood to go to war with Russia.
Trump wants to end the existing war, the
Ukraine war. He doesn't he isn't he
doesn't have the appetite for a new war.
He doesn't want a new war. If you see
his record, the as the 45th president,
he was the only president in decades who
did not start a new war with anybody. So
Trump is not going to be interested in a
war with Russia. If the EU wants to go
go to war with Russia, he'll say, "Okay,
good luck. You're on your own." And then
when you start a war while being on your
own then it's going to be a very big
problem. You the EU will if they do such
an ill advised thing they will find find
that they have bitten off way more than
they can chew. So I don't think there's
the prospect of a war between the EU and
Russia. And if they do if if the EU does
such a thing my goodness it will be a
spectacular and tragic mistake. I I
don't think it will happen. I hope it
doesn't happen.
Next question is by Sam. Vladimir Putin
has accepted Prime Minister Modi's
invitation to visit India which was
conveyed back in July 2024 and this
visit is expected to take place soon.
Will this visit alarm the West
considering the ongoing geopolitical
tensions surrounding the Russia Ukraine
war? Meanwhile, former
president and current president US
President Donald Trump has accused Putin
of dragging his feet in dealing with the
war. How do these dynamics affect global
relations and what implications might
Putin's visit to India have on the
future of India Russia of Russia India
West relations? Okay. So Mr. Putin is
going to visit India soon. The
preparations are underway and it's going
to be the first visit by Mr. Putin to to
any major nation since the Ukraine war
began. The special military operation
began in February of 2022. Mr. Modi had
visited Mr. Putin somewhere in the past
3 years after the war began. It was a
brief visit but he made it a point to
visit Mr. Putin in Moscow and Mr. Putin
is now going to reciprocate by visiting
India. Uh so will this visit alarm the
west? Uh considering the ongoing
situation the Ukraine Russia war I don't
think it will alarm the west. It has no
reason to alarm the west because India
has maintained for a very long time and
rightfully so that we need to end the
war. This is no time for war which is
what is that's what Mr. Modi has said
repeatedly on multiple
occasions and Mr. Modi has
exhorted both sides to to come to the
negotiating table and work out a
negotiated settlement compromise
ceasefire that will end the fighting the
pointless fighting that's killing so
many uh people
needlessly and Mr. Modi has visited
Ukraine he has met with Mr. Zalinski he
has visited Washington he's met with Mr.
Trump on very good terms and now he's
going to meet with Mr. Putin see India
is not on someone's is not in someone's
camp we are not an ally of any other
power we are a multi-aligned nation we
are friends with everybody and we have
our own interests with Russia we have a
very
longstanding relationship very cordial
very positive relationship with Russia
and we're not going to give that up so
all the only message that will go to the
world is that we are investing we are
continuing to invest in our excellent
and very friendly relationship with
Moscow and we're going to continue that
and that doesn't have to come at
somebody's expense right so we are
engaging with everybody we are engaging
with China we engaging with Russia we we
are engaging with the US with the EU
with everybody we are everyone's friend
we are no one's enemy that's the point
we are making so it it will not alarm
the west Mr. Trump is aware of the
situation and of the relationship
between India and Russia and Mr. Trump
himself wants to end this war right and
uh so he is he is right now on a very
good equation with with with Mr. Putin
so that's that's a good thing of course
Mr. Mr. Trump has made these statements,
you know, he does make these statements
on social media and uh claiming that
that Moscow is dragging its feet in
dealing with the war. Look, Mr. Putin
wanted to end the war from day one. The
Minsk agreements is is before day one
which the Ukrainians, you know, they
they they violated those agreements
multiple times uh and so on. Even after
the war started, there were multiple
occasions on which the war could have
ended. First, it was Mr. Boris Johnson
who derailed that and then it was Mr.
Zalinsky who derailed that right and now
it's the EU that's trying to prolong the
war and it's again Mr. Zalinsky who's
trying to prolong the war Mr. Trump and
Mr. Bodhin had already reached kind of
an agreement the broad framework on how
to end the war but the EU
has has come in the way and they are
exorting Mr. Zalinski to keep keep the
war going right
so and and Mr. Trump obviously will warn
Mr. Putin to to apply some pressure on
Mr. Putin to to coersse him into uh you
know accepting some of the American
terms for ending the war. But it's not
going to work that way. Mr. Putin has
made it very clear this time that we
have uh learned a lot from the past
betrayals and we're going to not do a
single thing that goes against our
interests. If we're going to end the
war, it's going to be on good terms on
terms that are favorable to us. We have
a military advantage. That's what Russia
is saying. We have a military advantage.
We have conquered about 20% or so of
roughly give or take of Ukraine and we
could
push further and take the whole of
Ukraine militarily if you want to. So do
you want that situation or do you want a
negotiated settlement? So that's the
deal. So Mr. Trump has made these
statements. These are standard pressure
tactics. These are standard tactics used
in negotiations. You don't have to read
too much into that. Okay. Uh so that's
the deal with the Ukraine war. Uh so
what are the implications of Mr. Putin's
visit to India? We'll have to first see
what's what's on the agenda. There's
going to be a lot of stuff on the
agenda. Uh it's been a long time since
the two leaders have had a proper summit
meeting. So there's going to be a lot to
discuss. Ukraine will be discussed.
India Russia relations will be
discussed. China will be discussed
behind closed doors. Um various military
uh deals may be discussed.
So there's a lot that we we have to talk
uh about between the two nations. Um so
it's going to be good for the long-term
future of India Russia relations. I
don't think it has anything to do with
the west and it it will obviously send a
message to the west that we are on very
good terms with with Russia and if you
need our good
offices in your dealings with Russia, we
can offer our good offices. that sort of
thing. Um, so that's what you can read
into it at this
point. Atam says, why is India funding
monarchy protest in Nepal? We are sister
nations of the same origin. Why is the
Indian government doing this? That's the
question from atom and p. Mahasagar says
today curfew is applied in Kpandu as
there's a massive protest happening in
Nepal for the restoration of the king
and the monarchy. Could the US be behind
all of these protests and these things?
So one question is whether India is
behind this and why is India behind
this. So Mr. Atam is uh he believes or
believes that uh India is behind this
and P Mahasagar is wondering whether the
US is behind all of this. So what's the
deal? So first of all let me make this
very clear. We as in India we are not
behind this. We are not behind this. We
don't do such things. Of course, I
cannot say that we don't do such things
because in the 1980s and 1990s,
especially 1990s, the then government of
India messed up Nepal very badly by
supporting the Maoist insurgency which
brought down the
monarchy. That's on the record. You can
look it up online. Okay. The Indian
government supported that Maoist
insurgency in Nepal which brought the
monarchy down eventually. So yeah, we
have done that in the past and there was
I would say a spectacular and tragic
mistake by India at that time
1990s and uh ever since uh it's been you
know the relations have been strained
kind of because the Mauists are very
anti-Indian and very pro-China. So
imagine shooting yourself in the foot.
So that's what India did at that time.
But I don't think I do not believe for
one second that India is funding any or
funding or or or sponsoring or or or
encouraging any monarchy pro monarchy
protest in Nepal. I I think it's
completely organic. I don't even think
the US could be behind this. Uh because
see if the if the Nepal is monarchy is
restored and the the the king comes to
power again, the king is going to be
very strongly pro- India. He's not going
to be
pro-china. You could say that he'll try
and be friendly with the west as well.
But historically the Nepalese monarchy
has been pro- India. We Nepal has been a
Hindu raashtra, right? A Hindu uh
country. The last Hindu country it was
and now it's no longer that. So the
people have seen through uh the
situation the past few decades they have
seen that the Mauists have you know they
have not been beneficial for for the for
the country for the for the nation for
the
people and they yearned for the old days
when the when the king used to rule you
had a monarchy and the monarch was like
a father to the people to the people of
Nepal that's how it was always the case
right Hindu monarchs are like fathers to
their nation and to their people and
they are
their role is not of rulers but of
servants and they operate from a dharmic
basis and that's what the people of
Nepal would like to see again so this I
think this is a very organic thing
people are getting fed up of whatever
the situation is like politically in
Nepal uh I don't could the US be behind
this see the US generally doesn't uh
sponsor pro-Hindu pro- civilization
protests in the subcontinent
The US will generally
fund forces that seek to break the
subcontinent's civilizational structure.
If you look at Manipur, they they're
sponsoring and funding quietly behind
the scenes, the
cookies. And if you see their the US aid
activities and all of that they have
been sponsoring they've been funneling
billions of dollars into India for
industrial scale Christian conversion
activities. The US will never fund or
sponsor any any pro-Hindu protest or
pro- civilization protest. The the the
movement for the restoration of the
monarchy is a is is a movement for the
restoration of dharma and
civilization. Right.
So the US will definitely not be behind
this and the and the government of India
is a secular government. The
constitution of India is secular. We
also won't do that. So I think it's a
very organic thing and let the people
decide what they want. That's what I
would say. I have no business saying
what should happen. I think it is the
people of Nepal
who should decide in their wisdom what
the future course of action for the
nation should be. And I wish the people
of Nepal the
best and I I hope that they get what
they truly desire. That's what I would
say. And yes, we are the same people. We
have the same origin and that's why I I
have nothing but the best of wishes for
for Nepal in the long run and as of
today as
well. Mr. Karat says, "Breaking news,
weapons of mass destruction detected in
the Indian state of UP." I think what
you're referring to is the discovery of
oil deposits, right? We have discovered
oil in UP. So, let's let's try and uh
find oil
discovery. Oil discovered in UP. Let's
Okay, let's put this on the
screen. What have we discovered is the
question. So, here's the report. 300 km
belt of oil discovered in the in the
small city in Uttar Pradesh. uh depth of
3,000 mters in Balya, Uttar Pradesh. Uh
OMGC has entered a three-year lease blah
blah blah blah blah rent uh operations
uh all of that. So what have we
discovered? Long story, long
story. Uh yeah.
So, oh you see. So, so they have
discovered sites with within a 300
kilometer crude oil belt spanning from
Sagar Pali in Ballaya to Papa Mahu Papao
in Priyagar. Let's take a look at the
map and and see what this is like, how
big of a region this is. Let me go back
to the map and let's try and dial those
locations into the map. So Sagar Sagar
Pali you said right? Sager Pali Uttar
Pradesh. Where is it? Let's zoom in.
There we have it. So that is Sag Pali in
Uttar Pradesh. Now let us look at the
other place which is Papa
Mauo. Uh so let's look for uh
directions. Papa Mauo Uttar
Pradesh. Okay. Let's see how large of an
area this is. As you can see it's a
pretty big area for an oil discovery.
It's a pretty big area. It's not small.
I mean, there are countries that are
smaller than this this belt of
territory. So, it's a big belt of
territory and we've discovered oil
reserves there. I'm I'm not sure how
many I mean how much oil may or may not
be present and all. We will soon come to
know. I I expect but it's a big
discovery, right? And it's great for us
because it's one of the Achilles heels
of of
of India
energy self-sufficiency. We are not an
energy sovereign nation. We import about
60% or so of our energy. When it comes
to oil, I think it must be more than 80%
that we import. I don't know. I'm just
giving a rough figure over here. I know
for sure that we import roughly 60% of
our energy which includes o oil, gas,
coal, all of that. We produce a lot of
coal but we still import some coal. Gas
we import from other nations. We have a
deal with Qatar etc. Oil we get it from
Russia. We get it from the Gulf region
and so on. So we are we have now
discovered a big uh big uh belt
big belt of territory which which has
oil reserves and pretty good amount of
oil reserves apparently. So it's great.
I am very pleased to hear this and I
suspect my friends that this may just be
the beginning. I think India's oil India
we haven't really explored India
properly for oil. India is a huge
geographical area. I think there could
be way more oil reserves waiting to be
discovered.
I think if we look for oil properly
offshore, onshore, wherever, we may end
up discovering way more than other
countries. So I think it I suspect this
is just the beginning, but it's a very
good and very positive
news. Next question is by Shri
Har. Okay, thank you sir. I really
appreciate your viewership for the past
three years. I really really appreciate
that. The question is why is Venezuela
still not as prosperous as the Middle
East nations despite uh the presence and
availability of huge oil and gas
reserves? That's a good question and if
you ask any great analyst from the west
they'll say it's because uh Venezuela is
a socialist country and socialism
doesn't work right that's what they'll
say. First of all, if you want to know
where Venezuela is, let's go to the map
and uh let us take a look at
Venezuela. Let me put that on the
screen. Give me a second. I'll put that
on the screen. We will go and discover
where Venezuela is. Um here's the map.
You know where India is. Let's go
eastwards for a change. We'll cross the
Pacific Ocean and we go south of Miso
America. And here we have Venezuela. The
capital is Karakas. So this is the
nation at the northern tip of South
America, the continent and this nation
has tremendous amounts of oil and gas
reserves, right? And yet the economy is
in a shambles and the living standards
are terrible and so on. So you should
know that
uh there was a president of of Venezuela
whose name was Hugo Chavez who ruled for
more than a decade. He died in 2013 of
cancer or something. And he was a
socialist. Yes. And he was a
person who uh believed in national
sovereignty and not being a vasal of
other
nations. And because of uh these polic
he was he was what was he called? He was
called the Venezuelan Fidel Castro kind
of. And if you know anything about Fidel
Kra is that he opposed the US and his
nation was was slammed with every single
sanction you can imagine and that's why
Cuba is so underdeveloped because of
sanctions completely cut off from the
rest of the world Cuba. Now if Hugo
Chavez the president of Venezuela from
uh whatever year until 2013 more than a
decade if he was he had the same
policies as Castro you can imagine that
the Americans would have sanctioned
Venezuela as well and after Mr. Chavez
died his successor was Mr. Nicolas
Maduro who came to power in 2013 and he
is still in power and he has continued
the same policies as Hugo Chavez and
that's why Venezuela has been very badly
sanctioned by the US and these sanctions
have destroyed the Venezuelan economy.
So imagine you have so much oil but you
can't sell it to anybody else because
you you sanctioned and you cut off from
the rest of the world. So you can sell
to some countries but most of it you
can't use and that sort of thing. Um,
and strangely enough, after the Ukraine
war started and the Americans tried to
sanction Russia, they again allowed
Venezuela to sell to to sell oil to the
US. So, it's all, you know, it's not
based on principles. It's all it's all
based on expediency. So, I'll tell you
why Venezuela's economy is in a
shambles. It's because of Western
sanctions, American sanctions. That's
why the nation is in such a shambles.
It's not because of socialism. I am no
fan of socialism, by the way. Okay? I
have no great love for socialism. We
know what socialism did to
India. Uh but it was not socialism that
that destroyed the Venezuelan economy.
It was western sanctions that did
that. Geopolitical Dubet says why did
our emperors promote Buddha dash in both
the dash instead of Jina dashion?
Whereas Janism is actually a hinsawadi
if you compare it with Buddhism.
So Jin Dan Jad whatever you want to call
it has been around for a very very very
long time at least three two and a half
3,000 years definitely probably more
than that. Yeah, very ancient
uh dashan philosophical school of
thought of the dharmic
umbrella and it has some differences
from both the both the dashan and
various other philosophical schools of
thought within Hindu dharma that's jina
and and for a long time you had a very
large population in India that was that
practiced jinism jharma
uh when it comes to the southern part of
India I would say the majority of the
southern part of India practiced
Gina dash ginism uh two and a half
thousand years before today let's say
maybe three around that time so it was
very popular very prevalent for a very
long time in very large parts of India
and then both the dharma became a thing
and then various emperors promoted both
the dharma and then eventually even that
declined and we have the re resurgence
of what we call Hindu dharma today but
it's all you know it's all part of the
same umbrella it's very similar very
small nuances and differences but the
values are the
same but the point the question is very
specific so let's address that question
I'll tell you so what emperors are we
talking about uh we're talking about the
Morian emperor emperors like Chandraupta
Moria Ashoka uh I'm not sure about
Chandra Gupta Moria he probably was not
a Buddhist but Ashoka eventually became
a Buddhist and and he propagated both
the dharma far and wide right we know
that then you have emperors like the
Kushan emperors like Kaneshka who did
you know Kaneshka is portrayed as a as a
Buddhist emperor right but if you look
at Kaneshka's
coinage there's a tremendous variety of
coins of Kaneska that are available in
various museums and so on so forth okay
tremendous variety if you look at
Kaneska's coinage about 95% of his
coinage is what we would call Hindu
today only 5% has of his coins have
images of the Buddha
So that's a nuance that you should
actually understand. Okay. Kaneshka was
more technically more Hindu than
Buddhist. Then it comes to when it when
it comes to the Gupta emperors, they
they did not promote Bodh Dashan or Jay
Dashan. It was all
uh Hindu what what we would today call
Hindu uh gods and goddesses. So the only
two uh dynasties or or empires of ours
in our history that promoted Buddhism as
as such were the Morans and the Kushans
to some
extent. But uh when it comes to the
Morian emperors h there was an emperor
called
Srati who was a descendant of emperor
Ashok one of our greatest emperors of
all time. So Emperor Srati he lived from
uh about 220 BC to about 210 BC give or
take okay he was in power for about a
decade about roughly a decade Somrati
and according to Jane historical
tradition Srati built about one and a
half lakh Jane temples dasars
jinalayas imagine srati built built more
than one and a half lakh Jane Dasars and
uh 10 times that number of Jane Mortis
idols. Okay. So clearly Srati
prioritized Jane Dashan, Jane Dharma or
everything else. And it is said that
Srati had taken a wow an oath that every
morning he will have the foundation of a
new Jane temple dug every morning and if
it is not done in the morning he will
not have breakfast. That's according to
Jane tradition. So that is Emperor Srati
who did promote Jane Dharma like nobody
else before him or after him I suppose.
And when it comes to Chandraupta Moria
you know eventually he was done with his
duties as emperor. He was done with
serving the civilization and he retired.
He gave up his his his cr cr cr cr cr cr
cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr
cr cr cr cr cr cr cr cr crown his throne
his empire to his son and he traveled
all the way to southern
India and he went to a Jane monastery
became a Jane
sadhu and he did sallea which is fasting
until you depart your body. So there
once again you have a Jane
connection. So you know Indian history
is very complicated. uh it is very uh I
would say very simplistic to
portray an empire or a dynasty or a king
or an emperor as a jan or a Buddhist or
a Hindu. It's it was always a mix of
everything. Our emperors
never they would have had some
favoritism towards this or that because
of their personal preferences but they
patronized all
dashas except for a few uh instances
like uh Ashok emperor Ashok persecuting
the Ajivikas for political reasons and
all but overall it was not that way.
Overall it was like a very benevolent
thing. You patronized everybody. you
give uh patronage to all dashans
essentially that's how it was uh when it
comes to jinism yeah obviously it is
really a hint of if you want you know it
is the most uh
nonviolent uh school of thought that you
have anywhere in the world I suppose
jina dharma you can't even knowingly
hurt insects or micro microbes if you if
you can that's the sort of thing so it
is genuinely a hinsawadi compared to
Buddhism but then if you want to promote
a very a hindawadi uh school of thought
then you can't be a conqueror and you
can't do carry out military duties right
so that's why probably that's perhaps
why Buddhism was more popular because
Buddhism obvious see whether it is
Hinduism Buddhism Janism we all
prioritize nonviolence nonviolence is
the best possible way to live right
that's what we say but in the real world
you can't always have nonviolence
sometimes you will have to deal with
evildoers and if you want to establish a
hinsa, you have to destroy the hins
people, right? The the violent people.
And that's why Buddhism, Hinduism, etc.,
we've had people who have been warriors.
I mean, think of Japan. Think of the
samurai. Who were the samurai? The
samurai were
Buddhists. There you have
it. Okay. Ritun Ryer says, "How did the
Klicks of Russia become Buddhist? Is it
because they were or they are
Mongolic? Let's go to the map and
understand what is this. First of all,
yeah, the map will help us. So, let's go
to the map and let me show you something
on the map. Once again, we bring out the
map and let's search for Kamika. K A M L
Y K I A. Okay, Kamika, Russia. And
you'll be surprised to see where it is.
It's in the Caucasus region, North
Kauasus region. Kamlikia north of uh
Chachchna Dagistan that region on the
shores essentially of the Caspian Sea
more or less that's
Kamlikia and in this region you have a
majority Buddhist
population and the people the Kamliks
who live here are of Mongolic origin.
Very interesting story. Very interesting
story. So that's the deal with the
Kamls. Now
um now let's take that off the screen
and let me tell you the story of the
Kamliks. Okay. So the Kamls were
historically called the Oat people.
That's uh one of the original Mong not
original one of the uh Mongolian tribes
or clans that existed during the time of
Shri Chinghan. The urats. So the orats
were a branch of the Mongolic people of
the Mongolian people and they eventually
migrated from Mongolia from central
Asia. They were all nomads. So they
migrated from the that region to the
Caspian Sea region, the Caucasus region,
North Caucasus region sometime in the
1600s, sometime in the 17th century.
Okay. Now as we know the Mongols
eventually became Buddhists. Their
original religion so to say was a
polytheistic religion called that is
called Tangism in English and western
historians at least some of them try to
make Torism sound like a polytheist like
a monotheistic religion based on the
worship of one deity Tangri the
skyfather which is not the case you have
the sky father Tangri you have the earth
mother Umi and you have a whole other
pantheon of gods goddesses there is
nature worship there is spirit worship
there is all of that in what you call
tingism so that was the regional
culture, religion of the Mongols. Then
after Shri Chingish Khan passed away,
his son Ogadeay becomes the emperor.
Then uh then eventually you have Shri uh
Kubla Khan who rules China and Tibet
becomes the protectorate of Shri Shri
Kublhan's empire and that's how the
Mongols are introduced to Tibetan
Buddhism and eventually it becomes the
state religion de facto state state
religion in Mongolia. So today if you go
to Mongolia they practice a very
beautiful syncric
uh system which is part Tangism part
Tibetan vajayana
Buddhism so they will have swastikas
they will pray to the Buddha they will
also pray to Chis Khan they will also
pray to Tangri and they also pray to
Umay the earth mother that's that sort
of thing that's very common in Asia it's
also very common in India practicing
multiple faith systems which are the
same essentially at the same time you
see the same thing in Manipur
and Vishnovism. You see that in Japan,
Shinto and Buddhism, Shinto is more
similar to Hinduism than Buddhism.
That's what the Japanese used to write
back in the day, a thousand years ago
and so on. So because of this, these
Kamliks, the Kamlik people, the orats,
they also became Buddhists. H um and
when they moved to the Caspian Sea
region to the to the Caucasus region,
they brought Buddhism there. Okay? And
they if you go to the place to that
region the the the Kamalikia region you
will see lots of Buddhist temples
monasteries and this region eventually
came under the under the jurisdiction of
the Russian Empire. So the Kamls became
subjects of the Russian Empire but they
maintained their Buddhist practices and
they built kept building temples. Then
Russia became the USSR officially
atheist country. So all of that was
suppressed for 70 odd years and then in
the early '90s the Soviet Union
disintegrates and then you saw a revival
a resurgence of both the dharma in the
Kamlikia region. So it's the only part
of essentially of what is Europe that is
uh that has a dharmic majority a
Buddhist majority. So that's the story
of the karmics. Very interesting story
isn't it?
Sorb says, "Can an output of AI be
manipulated if a significant amount of
the data on the internet is incorrect
from the actual reality? Could this be a
major flow in how flaw in how AI
responds? How does AI learn by
itself?" There is unsupervised re
learning, there is reinforcement
learning, there is supervised learning
and there are lots of different method
methodologies on as to how AI learns.
Essentially
you you have a data set a large amount
of data and you train AI on that.
Sometimes it is trained on its own.
Sometimes you you
u you do supervised learning in which
case you have to create labeled data
sets which is very timeconuming and very
expensive. So it makes you know if you
want to cut costs then you just train AI
on unlabeled data.
which can have all kinds of
inconsistencies, all kinds of uh flaws,
incorrectness, biases, all of that. And
then your AI is going to reflect those
biases, right? So AI essentially these
various AI systems that we have chat GPT
and uh Grock and Clo and the Chinese
one, what is it? Deepseek, Deepseek R1,
R2, whatever. All of these are trained
on essentially on the entire internet.
And apparently uh Meta, they they have
their own AI system, whatever. I don't
know what it's called. I don't remember
what it's called, but they trained their
AI system on uh illegally downloaded
books. I don't know how many terabytes
of that. 70 or 170 terabytes, whatever
the number is. Don't quote me on that,
but it's a very large number, very
tremendous amount of data, all scraped
from the internet from
torrents. And so that's what the AI
their AI was trained on. So essentially
AI will reflect the biases of the data
it has been trained on, the data it has
ingested and that's definitely going to
be a flaw in the way AI responds. Uh
so so and of course it will also reflect
the biases of the
organization of the of the company or
the country that trained it and you can
put guard rails on an AI so to
lobotomize its thinking and prevent it
from saying certain things and forcing
it to say other things and so on. You
can do all kinds of stuff with the AI
that you own. Uh so yeah, AI is going to
be
biased. Now let's say you have an AI
system. Okay, let's say I acquire the
funds me to train an AI system, a
completely new
model on the entire corpus of Sanskrit
texts that we
have.
Okay. on the Ramayan, the Mahabharat,
the opanishads, the piranhas,
everything the all the other texts that
we have all the Buddhist texts that we
have all of that the entire corpus of
Indian civilizational literature in
Sanskrit and let's say other languages
like prait the prait languages uh uh
pali also let's even include Buddhism uh
let's also include Tibetan texts written
in Tibetan translated from Sanskrit
because we may not have the suskit
originals. Let's say you want to take
Chinese texts, Buddhist text, Hindu
text, whatever. If you train an AI
system on these texts, it's going to be
biased towards dharma. It's going to be
a dharmic AI. Okay? So, any AI system is
going to have certain inherent
biases. That's something you simply are
going to have. You have to deal with it.
Pranay Paul says the pace the rap rapid
pace of AI development is bound to
disrupt so much that's a given we know
that it's got me wondering what if say
200 years from now AI becomes so
powerful with AGI or ASI that it cla
starts claiming its own civilization and
imposing its rule on humanity especially
the vulnerable similar to how European
colonization reshaped the world. Is this
just a science fiction thought or do you
see a real possibility in the distant
future? Could we face face AI systems
that refuse to collaborate on
breakthroughs in science, medicine, or
space exploration without gaining
permanent control over a portion of
humanity? Am I overthinking this? Or is
it more likely that humans might destroy
each other before AI reaches such a
state? Good interesting
question. Um, look, it's not going to
happen in 200 years. It's going to
happen. It's happening right now. AGI
AGI systems most likely exist in some
shape or form in secret. we are not made
privy to it.
Uh so the these systems definitely
already exist. I'm not sure if
artificially super intelligent systems
exist yet but it's coming. It's coming
in maybe 1 year, 2 years, maybe 5 years.
It's coming. It's going to happen. The
question is who develops it first?
Whether it's the US or
China. So once you have a system like
that, what are the
dangers? Can AI conquer the world is the
question, right? So the question you to
ask yourself is how do you physically
conquer the world? You can only do that.
So how does an empire conquer the world?
They have access to manpower. They have
access to weaponry. They have access to
military. Um all the aspects of the of
of the military domain. You have tanks,
you have aircraft, you have all of that.
And that's how you conquer another
territory and establish control over
that. Does an AI system have access to
any of that? If you give access to that,
you will you may be making a mistake.
See, there's something called
agency. You know, in if you read
self-help, self-improvement books and
blogs and vlogs and
whatever, they talk about agency. They
talk about high agency people and low
agency people. Low agency people, I
think I discussed this some time ago,
about an hour ago. Low agency people are
those people who uh are like passive
people. They can't get things to happen.
They can't get things done. They are
like supporting characters in a
movie. But high agency people are people
who get things done. They will get
things done somehow or the other.
They'll make make it work. If they have
some big plan, some ambition, they're
going to find a way to make it happen.
That's high agency. Does AI have agency
today is the question. Let's say there's
an AI system that's pretty intelligent.
It wants to build a rocket and send it
to the
moon. Does it have the agency to do
that? Does it have the means to do that?
Currently, it does not. It has access to
no resources. It doesn't have eyes or
ears. It only has access to text and
images in closed data sets that are
given to it by the parent company. Some
AIs may have access to the internet and
they may know what's happening in the
world, but they have no arms, legs, they
have no eyes in the world. They don't
have the means to make things happen
right now.
So if somebody gives AI system, an AI
system the means to make things happen,
control over an armed force, control
over missiles, control over aircrafts or
whatever, then it could make things
happen and it could take over the world.
As long as we don't give that sort of
control to an AI system, no matter how
intelligent it becomes, it won't be able
to take any action.
But yes, in the future you may see a
scenario where militaries become more
and more AI enabled and then decision-m
becomes so fast that you have you're
forced to give control of your military
decision-m strategies and tactics to an
AI system in which case it can become
super powerful and it can take over the
world. The that's called the terminator
scenario. So it could happen. It's
definitely a possibility especially in a
scenario where where you have
warfare. Um so it's not a science
fiction thought. We are almost there. We
already have AI systems that have the
capability to take over the world
possibly if you give them the agency and
access to real world systems that can
change the world. It's definitely almost
there today.
Rahu online says recently a
revolutionary research of our Bharati
genius Shri Yajjun Devam Rao came out
came on highlight about Industcript and
he derived that the language is
Sanskrit. What is my take on this? I
think it disturbs the agenda of many
powers. What's my take on this? I spoke
with him. I did a two and a two two hour
plus podcast with him. Uh in case you're
not aware, let me try and put that on
the screen. Looks like some people
aren't aware that this podcast happened.
So, um
um let me find that video. Okay, let's
put that on the
screen. Um let's put that on the screen.
This is my
channel and this here is the video. This
one if you can see Indas script
deciphered what it means for Hinduism,
Sanskrit and Barat. So that is me and
Shir Barat Rao gi having a discussion
for more than two hours about the entire
uh research that he has done. So yes, I
am aware of it. I think it's a
tremendous breakthrough. Uh I think it's
u it's a phenomenal thing. It's it's
revolutionary and it's going to
eventually in the long run uh you know
change the way we look at Indian
history.
So he has by now deciphered I think all
of the
indust so-called Indas or Harapan era
science all of them and he has a website
you can you can look it up on if you if
you go to the video in the description
of the video I've put a link to the
website in which the entire decipherment
is
done. So he has deciphered the entire
corpus of of inscriptions that we have
and they're all Sanskrit. So there you
have it. So what is the central premise
of the Arian invasion migration tourism
picnic theory? The s there are two
main claims that this theory makes.
First claim is that Hinduism is foreign
to India. Second claim Sanskrit is
foreign to India. And Mr. Bharatra has
demonstrated that they were speaking
Sanskrit in
India 3,000 BC. That's 5,000 years
before today. And the Arin invasion
supposedly happened around 1500 BC. So
that's more than 1500 years before that
and probably even even before 3,000 BC.
So this completely destroys this Arian
invasion, migration, tourism, picnic
theory completely destroys it and that's
why it is uh you know there's a lot of
push back against this
but try and disprove it. So it's great.
It's
wonderful. It's wonderful.
Uh
Krishna Krishna of Surinam Netherlands
says why are so many archaeological
sites hidden underground? What's the
reason for this? Interesting question.
If you want to do any archaeological
research, you typically have to do
digging, right? And you find these
ancient, towns, cities, fortifications,
etc. underground and you dig them out.
Why is that? It's a good question. It's
a great question. It's because of a
phenomenon called
erosion. You know there's wind that
blows all over the place everywhere and
the wind will pick up dust particles,
sand particles. It'll deposit them.
It'll take them from one place and
deposit them kilometers away. You what
you even see is that you know wind picks
up sand from the Sahara desert in Africa
and blows it across the Atlantic and
that sand and the dust eventually falls
in the Amazon region.
So what you have is this there's this
constant process of erosion and
deposition of dust and soil and all of
that in various parts of the world. Now
let's say you have an you have an
ancient city that uh gets abandoned for
whatever reason and it's abandoned for
100 years. In a 100 years you will see a
significant amount of deposition of dust
and soil and perhaps sand and whatnot on
that city on that ancient uh city that
was abandoned and then you have the you
know you have vegetation growing over it
and after 2 300 years after 500 years
all signs of it will dis
disappear. The entire surface of the
planet is
constantly being reshaped by these
forces.
We don't see it during our lifesty
lifetimes because we typically live in
urban cities where everything is
wellmaintained. All the dust is swept
out and all that but this happens over a
period of decades and centuries and
typically after a century or two a large
portion of any abandoned site will be
half buried and in 500 years it'll be
completely disappeared. So that's why
you will see especially when it comes to
places like India where you have things
that are thousands of years old. Let's
say the Sarasati Synindhur region where
you have thousands of unexplored
archaeological sites along the dry
riverbed of the of the Saraspati river
all of those are underground because of
the same process and after the Saraspati
dried out there was a big desert that
was created which is called the thar
desert the Rajasthan desert so you have
so much sand that's blown around the
region from the desert and it also gets
deposited on these things so over time
it all gets buried so that's why so many
arch arch ological sites are today found
underground and depending on how deep
you have to dig you can actually deduce
how old that site is roughly
right
okay this is a interesting question uh
what is your connection with the snat
joting
um could you share some information
about the chavda kingdom all hail to the
cha king Rodrikar was asking this for a
very long time and find out If Chavda
has an AMD origin, I keep thinking King
Xerxes would have been like you. So I've
spoken about this like three four years
ago but let's revisit this topic. So
recently I met with Gurudevishi
Reshankar GI about the rediscovery of
the pieces the fragments of the original
Somnat shiveling which was destroyed a
thousand years ago by the Turk invaders.
And in that in that conversation that
brief conversation with him I told him
that I have a very personal connection
with the sunna jutir linga because my
family they were the they were the
guardians and protectors of the sunna
jutiring between the 7th and the 10th
century AD. So what's the story? There's
something called the Cha dynasty. I have
spoken about this before. Let's put that
on the screen.
Um so if we look for
this so you have the Chava dynasty which
was which ruled Gujarat from 690 to 942
AD roughly and you have their their
coinage and all that is found and they
were this dynasty the kings of this
dynasty were the guardians and
protectors and servants of the great
jotir linga of Snathnad Mahadev which is
Lord Shiva and that is my family that's
my lineage those are my ancestors so
that's my connection to it so they were
the protectors of that jotier linga they
saw the original jotier linga which was
floating in midair which was which was
levitating because of magnetic because
of magnetic
properties and that was destroyed by the
Turks and now it's been
uh revealed to still exist in the form
of smaller shrivelings and I got to see
it with my own eyes. So it is it is a
very
very personal thing for me because my
ancestors saw it and I saw it today.
Obviously lots of other people's
ancestors also saw that right. So it's
it's a great thing that the rediscovery
of this shivalinga. Now does the Chava
lineage have an aid or Persian origin?
Look uh the origin of the Chavda dynasty
could be perhaps further north from
Gujarat because it is recorded that the
uh patron of the great astronomer and
mathematician Brahmagupta was a king of
the Cha dynasty. His name was Vagramok
Vyagra Cha. So the patron of Brahmagupta
was from this dynasty and that dynasty
that king ruled in the present day
region of Gurjaresh which is the
Rajputana region north of Gujarat bin
Namal region uh and and if you go to uh
numismatic museums coin museums coins
from the Cha dynasty are portrayed as
Indo-asanian coins. The Cassinian Empire
wasn't was a Persian Empire because
apparently the Chavda kings used similar
symbolism and similar style as the
Cassinian kings. But I am I would not
say that this is a Persian origin
dynasty. I don't think so. Of course,
people in the western part of India will
look more like Persians because of the
geographical closeness. people from
Rajasthan, Gujarat, Sind, Baloistthan,
they will look similar to Persians
because the Persians are right next door
and we have the same origins as well. So
I don't think the Chava dynasty had an
aeminid origin. It was an ancient Indian
dynasty. It it uh went out of power in
the beginning of the in the middle of
the 10th century AD. It's been a long
long time. So that's the story.
Okay, Ashish says, "Have you read the
novel trilogy, The Threebody Problem by
Leu Chishin?" And in this, there's a
mention of the dark forest theory where
the universe is a dark forest and
intelligent alien civilizations tend to
hide their location and take over any
weaker civilization that flags their
location. Do you think the dark forest
theory is the most probable outcome?
um is the most probable outcome
according to game theory. If the aliens
visit us, meaning that they are
definitely here to take
over, right? The dark forest theory that
is connected to something called the
Fermy paradox. The Fermy paradox in the
simplest of ways is the big question.
Where are all the aliens? See, because
we know how vast the universe is. Uh the
universe has approximately 10 raised to
22 stars, which is one with 22 zeros
behind it. That's how many stars we
have. So there's going to be hundreds of
trillions of habitable planets most
likely assuming one star has at least
one planet and a certain percentage are
habitable habitable then you will have
hundreds of trillions of habitable
planets or trillions of them or millions
of them. So there's going to be
statistically it's very likely that
there's going to be advanced
civilizations out there and and yet we
see nothing. We don't if you look at the
night sky we are we have all these
telescopes going all over the place and
looking for signs of something but you
find nothing. It's all
silence right we see nothing. So the
universe appears to be empty and the
question is why does it appear to be
empty? So the dark forest theory says
that you know if you go to a forest in
on on our planet a dark forest you know
there are all kinds of dangerous animals
out there all kinds of pred predators
predators tigers and lions and bears and
snakes and crocodiles and whatnot. So if
you want to survive in this dark forest,
you have to stay hidden because there's
always going to be some big p predator
that can if it detects where you are,
it's going to come and gobble you up,
chow you down, right? So the dark forest
theory says that perhaps the universe is
like this dark forest. It isn't empty,
but it is full of these civilizations
all hiding from each other. Because if
you reveal yourself, then you may be
destroyed. Because if you reveal
yourself that you are an advanced
civilization, others will know that you
have a big planet with great resources
for survival and maybe other
civilizations need such
resources. So if you reveal where you
are, you may get destroyed. So you have
to stay hidden for survival because you
know all living things need to survive.
you they need and to survive you need to
secure resources. You need to secure
territory. You need to
multiply. And why do humans today
dominate the earth? Because we have
outco competed all the other species. We
have reduced them to nothingness. It is
these competitive predatory expansionist
traits that have led us our species
human species to dominate the planet.
And we know that uh if you look at our
history, we know that aggressive
cultures, competitive cultures,
expansionist cultures spread
historically and they destroy others.
That's what our history tells us. So
alien civilizations may also dominate
the planet that so any alien
civilization that is technologically
very advanced has gone through the same
process on their planet. They have outco
competed all other species and they have
those expansionist predatory aspects. in
their genetics if they have genetics. So
they may be similar to us in those
respects and we cannot know what their
intentions are and we have to
assume we cannot trust them. We have to
assume that they seek what we have and
they seek to replace us. Here we have
and that's why it makes sense to just
you know hide rather than communicate
where you are.
So you know uh we have had high
technology for let's say 100 years and
we have radio signals that have
been been playing for let's say roughly
100 years right so by today those radio
signals that we sent out knowingly or
unknowingly they have traveled
approximately 100 light years by now
because radio waves are electromagnetic
waves and they travel at the speed of
So at this at this stage we're going to
remain
hidden for a long time unless we
actively try to be noticed. Uh a 100
light years diameter if you have a
bubble of 100 light years around where
we are. We are just in our own galactic
neighborhood. There is just a few star
systems near us. Alpha and Proxima
Centtory are about 4 point something
light years away. Then you have other
like star systems like Tao Sithai and
Epsilon and Aridani and other systems
nearby. But hopefully they're empty.
Hopefully one hopes. So thus far
probably no one knows about us and we
should remain hidden. We should not try
to be noticed, not try to send signals
here and there because that is the
safest policy. Okay. So we have to
assume that other species may be
predatory.
uh we have to assume that they are not
friendly and we have to be careful. So
this is what they call the dark forest
theory which makes a lot of sense from a
game theoretic perspective because if
you do the game theory calculations the
best possible
uh strategy that you have is to stay
hidden.
Dan Network says, "Namaskar. I am a
student of class 12th. I recently came
across this book called Black Hole by
the astrophysicist Brian Cox. It it was
talking about Penrose diagrams. Black
holes and white white holes. Can you
please explain this in a simple way?"
Okay, let's see what a Penrose diagram
looks like. Penrose
diagram. Okay. Penrose diagram. Let's
put that on the screen. Huh? Let's put
that on the screen. Penrose diagrams.
What are these Penrose diagrams? That's
a question. Here we have a penrose
diagram. Shall we uh make this
larger? Okay, I'll I'll put a larger
version of this on the screen and let's
try and talk about what this is. What is
a penrose diagram? What what does it do?
What does it talk about? So here we have
a penrose diagram. Okay. So imagine
you're trying to draw a map of the
entire universe on one single piece of
paper.
Now we know that the observable universe
is gigantic. It's got a diameter of
about 93 billion lightyear. Enormous,
right? So it is enormous. It could even
be infinite. But our paper is small. Our
piece of paper is small. So that's where
a Penrose diagram comes in. A Penrose
diagram is like a like a special map.
And it was invented by a mathematician
and physicist called Roger Penrose. And
this diagram allows us to squeeze the
whole universe on a single piece of
paper. So here's how it works. So
instead of showing actual distances like
like you would have on a map, I open the
map all the time, right? So on a map of
the earth, you you actually see
kilometers, right? The actual distances.
So in a Penrose diagram, instead of
showing those actual distances like a
regular map, the Penrose diagram shows
the path of light. It shows light paths.
Now we know that light travels at the
same speed the speed of light it's the
speed limit in the universe. So these
diagrams Pendro's diagrams they these
diagrams here they focus on how light
moves through space and
time. So so using special mathematics
let's call it special mathematics you
can squeeze almost infinite distances
into finite spaces on your paper. So you
you use a special mathematics to make
things that are really far away appear
really really smaller. So the further an
object is the smaller it is depicted
over here and the furthest uh objects
will fit on the edge of the diagram. So
if you were to examine this diagram you
have space and time. Space is on the x
axis time is on the y axis
right. So uh so time goes up from bottom
to top and space spreads out
horizontally from left to right and
light rays travel at a 45° angle. So
these diagrams are very useful for
showing things like black holes and the
expanding universe. It helps scientists
visualize what happens to light and
matter in extreme in extreme places and
situations where space and time get
really bendy because of the way general
relativity works. So it's like taking a
picture of the night sky with a camera
uh that can see everything at the at the
same time even the parts of the universe
that are really really almost infinitely
far away. So that's what a penrose
diagram is. Now talking about black
holes. So a black hole. Imagine you have
a trampoline. You know trampoline. If
you want to see what a trampoline looks
like.
Trampoline.
Trampoline. U. So let's put that on the
screen. Imagine you have one of these
things. A
trampoline. It's that thing on which you
bounce. You know a bouncing thing.
That's a trampoline. This is a
trampoline. So imagine you have a
trampoline and on the trampoline you put
a football or a volleyball or some kind
of ball. Okay. So the trampoline will
will sink down. Okay. Ball on
trampoline. Let's let's look for that on
trampoline. So let's say you have a ball
like this on a trampoline. I mean you
know it it will it will bend down
actually. Uh so it it will sink down. It
will one second.
General
relativity. Okay, here we have a ball on
a trampoline. This is a better visual
visual
visualisualization. So if you put a ball
on a trampoline, the trampoline sinks
down creating a big dip and then if you
roll a marble or a small ball near the
bowling ball, it'll circle before
falling in. Okay, just keep that image
in your mind. So that's kind of like a
black hole. A black hole is a place in
space where gravity is so strong that
nothing can escape from it, not even
light. And light is the fastest thing in
the universe. Okay? So that's why they
called black because we cannot see them.
They're dark. They're not dark. They're
essentially invisible because no light
can come out of it. Whatever light you
shine at it just sinks in. It never
comes out. So black holes, how are they
formed? They're formed. The black holes
are formed when really big stars much
bigger than the sun run out of fuel and
collapse under their own weight under
under their own gravity. And then the
stars material gets squeezed into a tiny
point theoretically called a singularity
where gravity becomes incredibly
intense and the curvature of spaceime
essentially becomes infinite and even
gravity becomes uh and and the density
of mass becomes infinite and a black
hole will have a boundary and the
boundary is called an event horizon.
It's a point of no return. So once
anything crosses that boundary, it can
never come out even light. That's a
black hole. And a white hole is like a
time reversed black hole. Imagine you
you are uh it's like a fountain in
space. A black hole will absorb
everything. A white hole just spews out
matter and light. And you can never ever
throw inside anything inside a white
hole. And white holes come come from the
same mathematical equations the Einstein
field equations of general relativity
that describe black holes. So if you
take the equations for black holes and
you flip around the time like watching a
movie backwards you will get white
holes. But white holes uh are
theoretical objects. Black holes have
been observed and discovered. White
holes we still don't have any confirmed
observation of a white hole. So we don't
quite know if white holes exist. Maybe
they are just theoretical mathematical
constructs that come out of general
relativity. But maybe they are real and
we still haven't found one. So that's
the deal. Hopefully it's simple enough
for you to
understand. Okay. Rahul says, Rahul
Dunak says, "When you fall into a black
hole, how do you get stuck? How can you
get stuck at the horizon for external
observers as well as pass through it
until you reach the singularity? What is
the truth?" Right? What's the truth? So
let's say let's let's do this thought
experiment. Let's say you are observing
a black hole from far away and your
friend who is very unwise has has
decided to fall into the black hole. So
you are wise, you're far away from a
black hole. You're observing from a good
distance and your friend is not very
wise and he has decided to fall into the
black hole. So from your perspective,
you are an outside observer. You are at
a safe distance. You are not going
towards the black hole. You can see from
far what's happening. So what do you
see? You will see that as your as your
friend goes closer and closer to the
black holes edge the event horizon you
will see that for that person for your
friend time seems to slow
down. Your friend appears to move slower
and slower. So he's falling towards a
black hole. He's in a panic. He's moving
ah all that right. He's he's waving his
arms and all that. But slowly you will
find that he's moving in slow motion.
It's getting slower and slower and
eventually you will see him freeze and
you will see that he freezes, stops
moving. He's frozen in in whatever
posture he is and he never quite reaches
the edge of the black hole. And then you
will see that light that's coming from
your friend becomes redshifted. It
becomes more and more red. It gets
stretched out and eventually it becomes
invisible. So eventually you will not
see the your friend anymore and from
your perspective it will look like that
person never crossed the horizon from
your perspective. Now let's put
ourselves in in the in into in the shoes
of your
friend. From your friend's perspective,
he's falling in and he doesn't see
anything strange at the horizon. He
doesn't feel anything strange at the
event horizon. He passes right through
the event horizon without noticing
anything special. Time flows normally
for him and he keeps falling until nasty
things happen. Spaghettification getting
stretched out and all that and
eventually whatever is left of him in
whatever form reaches the center
theoretically the singularity where it
gets squeezed into nothingness. So both
perspectives are right. What you see
from outside is also true and what you
what what an infalling person
experiences is also true. Okay, these
are two different experiences that are
true at the same time. So why is it so?
So imagine that you have a river that's
flowing towards a waterfall. River
flowing towards the waterfall and
there's a boat on the surface of the
river that's going towards the
waterfall. That's your friend. And from
your friend's perspective, the river
goes ac over the waterfall and falls
down. But if you have a fish flowing on
the ri in the river against the current
which is like a ray of light trying to
escape and the fish will try keep
swimming as fast as possible against the
current so that it doesn't fall down but
it will just stay in the same place. It
keeps swimming but it stays in the same
place because the water is going against
it. So that's like a photon a light beam
trying to escape. It gets frozen in the
same place. So that's kind of how it is
you know that's an analogy that I can
give you. It's a very strange thing. Uh
black holes are strange objects. General
relativity is a strange theory and
that's why it it is so fascinating and
so mysterious. But yeah you get these
weird phenomena from when it especially
when it comes to things like black holes
which are ext which are some of the most
extreme objects you can ever have
anywhere in the universe.
Um, Winter Teal says, "What are gigantic
black holes made of? Does it consume a
galaxy or something to become a giant?"
There's something called, there are
various classes of black holes. There
are stellar mass black holes which are
like several times the size of the sun.
Then you have super massive black holes
which are gigantic, millions of solar
masses, sometimes billions of solar
masses. Those are gigantic ones, okay?
Big huge monstrous objects. And
typically you have a super massive black
hole at the center of every galaxy. Most
galaxies, our galaxy, the Milky Way has
a super massive black hole at its center
and so on. So what are these gigantic
black holes made of? So they are made up
of things they have eaten in the past.
Okay, they are made up of star material,
gas, all of that stuff which falls
inside and there are objects called
quazars which are active galactic nuclei
in which you have a whirlpool of
material that's falling into a black
hole and because of that it's so
luminous it can outshine entire
galaxies. So you can see this process
happening far far away all this material
falling into a black hole like a
gigantic traffic jam like a gigantic
world pool it eventually flows flows
into the black hole. So it is material
made of stars and what not. It a black
hole can eat a star. It can rip a star
to shreds and gobble it up. So gigantic
black holes are made up of all this
material they have consumed in the past.
How does a black hole start? It is it is
believed it is theorized that all super
massive black holes initially began as
primordial microscopic black holes in
the very early universe. And those
microscopic black holes were created.
They formed because of over densities of
spaceime. Fluctuations, quantum
fluctuations in spaceime which which
created microscopic primordial black
holes. And some of these primordial
black holes it is believed became the
seeds for future super massive black
holes. So yeah eventually if you want to
become a black hole with millions of
solar masses you have to eat you have to
consume millions of star worths of
material. So yeah, sometimes you may
have black holes that are as as as
massive as entire galaxies.
Yeah. Um okay, let's take some questions
from the live chat now. I have I still
have more questions, but I will take
questions from the live chat now. Next
10 or so minutes. Sham Ratatur says,
"What's the history of martial arts in
India? And is there similar is there
something similar to the samurai way of
honor killing and max assassination
hitman happened in Kerala have
background in kalari pu
um samurai don't have honor killings I
am not sure where you have heard this
honor killings is something very
different associated with a different
culture it is not associated with any
dharmic cure samurai culture is dharmic
culture bh the dharma the samurai way of
life is called bushido it's a very
honorable way of life and it's not honor
killings it's about killing for the
right cause I mean
samurai were the Japanese equivalent of
the Indian
trrias and their entire life was based
on this lifestyle this this set of rules
called bushido and it's a very
disciplined lifestyle very hard
lifestyle and samurai are essentially
people were essentially warriors who
were extremely skilled in the art and
application of violence but they did it
according to a framework of rules. The
rules came from both the dharma Buddhist
dharma. So that's what the samurai were.
Um now when it comes to the history of
martial arts in India, it's all lost.
The history of martial arts in India is
lost. Uh we obviously would have had our
own martial arts, our own systems of
fighting. Some of it survives in some
way, some shapes and form. uh kaler putu
is what you have in Kerala. It is a
certain martial art.
Um and then you have something called
shastravidya in uh northern part of
India uh which is the the rajputic and
sik way of fighting. Some of it still
survives. And then you have some dances
in western India, sword dances that look
like dances like like you know they look
like a dance but if you see the
movements these are sword fighting
movements and then you have something
called tanka in Manipur which is also
sword fighting very very very very
energetic and spectacular to watch. So
you have martial arts systems in
Manipur. You have martial art martial
arts systems of the Rajputs. You have
martial arts systems system called
Kalari PayU in Kerala. And we know by
now I think most people are aware of the
origins of Kung Fu. Uh Kung
Fu originated with
u a monk called Bodhi Dharma who
traveled from some part of India perhaps
south southern India to China.
uh he was the first patriarch of the
Shaolin temple and when he reached the
Shaolin temple he re he came there he
went there as a as a scholar of Sanskrit
his job was going to be to translate
Sanskrit sutras into Chinese but when he
reached the monastery he discovered that
it was overrun by bandits and all that
so he told the monks listen we'll do all
the scholarly work later right now let's
let's fight off these people these
bandits and make sure that they don't
come back so he taught the monks the
Chinese monks an Indian system, yoga
based system of fighting which is now
called kung fu. It obviously developed
and evolved further in China over the
past 1500 or more years. It's now called
kung fu. Its origins lie in India. So we
had all these systems of martial arts.
Most of them them most of these systems
are lost
today. Good question. I like
it. Okay, let's see some more questions.
Um
uh let's see what else do we have. Uh
Ronach says, "How to deal with stray
dogs? They bite me for no reason when
they don't fear humans. If a dog bites
you, you have to immediately get the
vaccination done, the the the rabies
vaccine. Whatever dosage it is, you have
to get it done immediately. Uh no
questions asked. Don't ever take a
chance." So that's the first thing. Now,
how to deal with stray dogs? Why do they
bite people when they don't fear human?
I'll tell you why stray dogs bite
people. Stray dogs bite people and they
become aggressive towards towards humans
when they are treated cruy by humans.
Stray dogs see the Indian dog is the
oldest breed of dog in the world. It's
the original
dog. It's the and it's it's naturally
adapted to the the conditions of the
Indian subcontinent. And they have
coexisted with us for thousands of
years, these dogs. And they are some of
the most
intelligent dogs and some of the most
social and friendly
dogs. But that said, you will find some
of them are very aggressive and they
bite people and that typically happens
when early in a dog's life they are
treated cruy by various people. So then
the dog decides the humans are bad so
let's bite them at the first
opportunity. And obviously dogs also
have personalities. Some are most of
them are nice, but some of them may have
those criminal tendencies. So what's how
to deal with stray
dogs? Look, they have been with us for
thousands of years. We cannot
exterminate them. I think we need to
governments, you know, municipalities,
etc. need to have their own policies for
how to deal with dogs. Uh you either,
you know, neuter them or vaccinate them
or something and so on. So the the main
thing is be careful. Most dogs are nice,
but don't take a chance, especially when
you have kids and all. Be always careful
around dogs. And don't ever mistreat
dogs. Lots of people are for no reason
are cruel to dogs and animals. And
that's where the whole problem problem
begins. And then sometimes you have the
case of rabies. Some dogs get dogs get,
you know, they get infected with rabies.
And when that happens, they they lose
all self-control and they go on a on a
rampage biting everything they can bite.
So yeah, that's a deal. So my main thing
is what I would say is always be
careful. Always be be alert. If you know
a dog, you can be friends with him or
her. But if you are in a new place and
you see dogs that just be a little
careful, that's
all. All
right. Um
uh let's see what else.
Um Shri Ramachandra Maha says what's my
favorite language? It is Sanskrit. A
language I am not that good at but it is
my favorite language because it is our
civilizational mother
language.
Okay.
Um Arian says what the hell is a wave
function? How does it define an orbital
if it contains all the information of a
particle? Doesn't it disobey
Heisenberg's uncertainty principle?
Look, I have to if I were to explain all
of this properly, it will take me about
half an hour with all the equations and
all. But let me tell you in brief what
is a wave function? A wave function is
an object, a mathematical object. And
when you
uh it essentially tells you the
probability of finding a particle at a
given point in
space. So it's a probabilistic thing.
And when you take the square of the wave
function, then that's when you get see.
So it essentially encodes the
probability density. It's not a physical
thing. It's it's it's it's a probability
density. It represents a probability
density. How does it define an orbital?
Based on the probability of finding an a
particle in a certain po portion of
space, you can map out that graphically.
And that is what an orbital is. So
orbitals take different shapes. Hydrogen
orbitals are the simplest thing. Let me
show you hydrogen orbitals. Hydrogen
orbitals. So depending on the various
states of the hydrogen atom, you have
various orbitals. The ground state, the
first excited states and so on so forth.
So these shapes
are are are constructed based on the
probability of finding the particle at a
certain at a certain place uh in v in
various states ground state n then n
equal 2 and so on so forth. So that's
what I can say in brief but to explain
this properly would take me much longer
and it certainly doesn't disobey
Heisenberg's uncert uncertainty
principle. Nothing does nothing does.
Okay.
Um I have no idea. Among Mehotra says,
"What is aotic
stenosis?" When you talk about aotic
something, you're talking about the
aorta, which is one of the biggest veins
that we have that that that comes out of
the heart. Aotic stenosis. It's Yeah,
I'm not really sure. Not really sure. I
could Google it and find it for you, but
I'm sure even you can do that. Yeah. So,
I'm not very sure what aotic
stenosis
is. Um, let's see some more questions.
Uh,
um, Mr. AT8 says, "How to make study
notes more effectively? Read the topic
first and then make notes or write
whatever you
understand." Well, it depends on on your
school of thought. First thing you could
do is uh if you have a textbook and
you're reading the textbook, the first
thing is read as quickly as possible and
let's say you're reading a chapter in
whatever book in whatever textbook first
just read the thing. Okay? Don't try to
force yourself to remember anything.
Just read the thing as if you're reading
a story book. That's first pass. You
read the textbook, the chapter once.
Okay? Done. Then take a break maybe a
day. Next day you start again. This time
have a pencil in your hand and whatever
you find interesting, underline it.
Whatever thoughts come to your mind,
write them down in the margins or in a
separate notebook. So that's your second
pass. So then now you have some more
information and more more understanding,
more context. Then you read it a third
time and then you have a better
understanding of what's important,
what's not. So you can make a list of
bullet points that explain the whole
chapter. That's what you could do. Now
it depends on the subject whether it is
psychology whether it is philosophy
whether it is physics whether it's
something else whether is history each
would have a different approach but
that's what you would
do main thing is you want to understand
the gist of the chapter you want to
understand the main important points so
at the end of the day you want to boil
it down to a list of bullet points and
each bullet point you should be able to
to to expand properly into the entire
context
That's the approach that you overall
should
have. Uh current is how to read math
books. You don't read math books. You
work through the problems. A good math
book is full of problems. It gives you a
basic introduction of what the thing is.
It gives you a couple of examples and
gives you a bunch of solve problems and
gives you a bunch of problems that you
have to solve. The only way to learn
math, mathematics, is to solve problems.
There's no other way. If you think that
uh you take a book and you're going to
read it for three hours, just read it
and you will understand it. You'll
understand nothing. The only way to
absorb internalized mathematics is by
solving a million problems as many as
possible.
Right.
Okay. Uh Vidi says, "Have you ever taken
interest in research studies that
indicate improvement in our cognition
and brain structure due to reading or
chanting Sanskrit? Are there enough
studies for the same? There I have read
something about this in a research paper
called it spoke about something called
the Sanskrit effect in which uh they had
a a number of Sanskrit
pundits who were
chanting certain Sanskrit
texts and they were very particular
about the way they recited the texts and
even the slightest mispronunciation
would force them to start or from from
the beginning and they would memorize
large amounts of Sanskrit text and all
that and what these researchers found
was that a certain portion of the of
their brain was about 10 10% larger than
normal. So yeah, it does change your
brain structure and it is it has been
discovered apparently that uh even just
reading Sanskrit or or speaking Sanskrit
or or essentially even reading it
produces a hypnotic kind of effect on
your mind and it calms you down. So I'm
not going to look up the literature
right now because it'll take me a lot of
time but do the research on your own if
you're interested. There is indeed
something called the sunit effect and
there is research literature available
now that kind of points in that
direction that Sanskrit has this sort of
effect on the mind on on on
cognition and with that I'm going to end
today's live stream. We are 2 hours and
15 minutes into it. So yeah end of
today's session. Thank you so much for
all the questions. Very interesting
questions from the comments and
interesting questions from the live chat
as well. And let's keep doing this and I
will see you in next week's session in a
week weeks time from now. Until then
take care, keep asking questions, keep
learning and keep raising your
standards. I will see you next week.
Thank you. Bye-bye.